<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An alarm to the vvorld, of the appearing of Sions king. Or, a brief discoverie of the foot-steps of the Lord upon earth.</title>
            <author>Banaster, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78065</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B631</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E550_24</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205655</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864973</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864973</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117206</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78065)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117206)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 85:E550[24])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An alarm to the vvorld, of the appearing of Sions king. Or, a brief discoverie of the foot-steps of the Lord upon earth.</title>
                  <author>Banaster, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, at the Black-spred-eagle at the West-end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A2 signed: Thomas Banaster.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 16".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117206:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>AN ALARM TO THE VVORLD, OF THE Appearing of Sions KING. OR, A brief Diſcoverie of the foot-ſteps of the Lord upon EARTH.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 24. 19.</bibl>
               <p>The Earth is utterly broken down, the Earth is clean diſſolved.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. 6.</bibl>
               <p>And at midnight there was a crie made, behold the Bridegroome cometh, goe ye out to meet him.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. 15.</bibl>
               <p>Behold I come as a thief, bleſed is he that watcheth, and keepeth his garments, leſt he walk naked, and I ſee his ſhame.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed for</hi> Giles Calvert, <hi>at the Black-ſpred-Eagle at the Weſt-end of</hi> Pauls, 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:117206:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117206:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honored Friend.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen thou openeſt this little Book, for to travel through it, if thou meeteſt with any thing, that thy heart cannot cloſe with, (as poſſibly thou mayſt) yet let thy heart reſpect thy friend, who hath writ his heart to thee, and watered the lines with his tears, by reaſon of beholding the earth watered with blood, I, with the blood of Kings, Princes, and mighty ones of the Earth, and yet further he will proceed in blood, even to the horſe bridles, and what I have writ, I have writ not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the perſon of any man, but out of pure love to all, and in love I have told you in part what you are, and what I am my ſelf, and in part what will become of us all; I have not written any thing in the leaſt againſt Kings, and powers, with a grudging heart, or a ſcorning of Kingly Authoritie; but exceedingly honoring them all, and by this it is manifeſt, in giving you notice and warning of the great Kings coming, who is the King of Kings, and therefore will unthrone all Kings, and overturn all Kingdomes, and all powers, and none but the Lords King and Kingdome ſhall ſtand. Friend, Thou wilt finde ſomething written in a very myſterious way; But time ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, and dayes to come ſhall bring forth to the view and knolwedg of all, every myſterious truth of God, eſpecially to them who are ſaved, and called with a holy calling; And therefore in the holy number, if thou art one of the holy number, thou art honored with a Princely name, which name is <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and it belongs as a gift given to the Princes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to know the myſteries, the very inſide myſteries of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven, where Chriſt thy King hath dwelt, ever ſince his aſcending, but now ready to be revealed in theſe our dayes, being the laſt dayes of the laſt dayes, in the which all things that are written ſhall be fulfilled, even ſo Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THOMAS BANASTER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:117206:3"/>
            <p>TO all Emperours, Kings, Princes, Rulers, Iudges, Magiſtrates, and Powers throughout the earth, after what name or Title ſoever mentioned, with all Miniſters and people, high, low, rich, poore, noble, and ignoble, and thou <hi>Iſrael</hi> amongſt the reſt, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole inhabitable parts of the world, do I ſend greeting, with a word (Behold the King of Kings is coming now with Clouds to viſit you) and by and by with light.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THOMAS BANASTER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117206:3"/>
            <head>AN ALARM TO THE VVORLD, OF THE Appearing of Sions KING.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Revelation 1. 7. verſe.</bibl>
               <q>Behold he cometh with Clouds, and every eye ſhall ſee him, and they alſo which pierced him, and all kindreds of the Earth ſhall waile becauſe of him, even ſo Amen.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereſoever you finde the word <hi>(behold)</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, you finde ſomething more then ordinary following it, ſomething very excellent, very admirable, and wonderfull, and alſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing very terrifying and amazing, by reaſon of the great deſtruction which attends it: which things at their appearing let them be either joyous or grievous, they will cauſe great admiration, great wondering and great aſtoniſhment, upon all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and paleneſs upon all faces: here followeth this word <hi>(be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold)</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:117206:4"/> joy, peace, reſt, ſalvation with eternall glory; alſo fear, trouble, confuſion plagues, Judgments with eternal miſery. Therefore Hear ye diſpiſers, and wonder, and periſh; and hear ye Saints, and in hearing rejoyce, and bleſſe his name who is your King, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now with clouds; which appearing will cauſe great joy of heart, and great ſorrow of heart; ye ſhall joy for joy of heart, and they ſhall ſorrow for ſorrow of heart; for here is life and death, joy and peace haſting on apace; for the Lords warning peece is ſhot off upon the world, to give warning to the world of the coming of Jeſus Chriſt, and that there is ſuch a thing, reade <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 20. <hi>Our converſation is in Heaven from whence we look for the Saviour. Heb.</hi> 9. 28. <hi>And unto them that look for him, he ſhall appear the ſecond time, &amp;c Titus</hi> 2. 13. <hi>Looking for the bleſſed hope and glorious appearing of the great God, Revel.</hi> 22. 20. <hi>Loe I come quickly, even ſo come Lord Jeſus;</hi> This coming of Jeſus Chriſt will be a coming to the purpoſe; his ſecond coming therefore hear ye ſons and daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> your King is come, and yet coming ſtill, but it is a cloudy coming or appearing. He that you have waited for ſo long, and looked for with ſo many a long look, with fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of many a long ſigh and groane, and in the bottome of your ſigh was written, Lord! when wilt thou appear? why, behold he is now coming to thee, oh thou afflicted ſoul, to eaſe thee of all thy troubles, and to deliver thee from al thy many ſufferings, which thou haſt ſuffered, for this many thouſand years, by thy own evill heart and fleſhly minde, and alſo by wicked men, which hated thee and thy King; therefore now lift up your heads, and caſt ſorrow from your heart, for he that is your joy, is deſcended the ſecond time, behold he cometh.</p>
            <p>Here are three things conſiderable in theſe words, firſt, who it is that proclaims this news, with a <hi>behold he cometh,</hi> it is the Lord by the mouth of <hi>John.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, what it is he proclaimes, it is of the coming of Ieſus Chriſt, Sions King.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to whom it is proclaimed, it is to all the world, good and bad, godly and prophane, and the reaſon why it is proclaimed to all, is, becauſe all ſhall ſee him, <hi>and every eye ſhall ſee him;</hi> The firſt appearing of this King is a cloudy appearing, and this cloudy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing, will be a dark, tempeſtuous, confuſed, and deſtructive ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117206:4"/> and alſo bloudy, and for the proofe of this, read <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 50. 3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97. 1. <hi>The Lord raignes, let the earth rejoyce, and the multitude of the Iſles be glad thereof, clouds and darkneſs are round about him,</hi> and <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 18. 9. <hi>The Lord bowed the Heavens and came down, and darkneſs was under his feet.</hi> This Scripture is fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in this your dayes the ſecond time, and then it will be finiſhed; The Lord raigns, do not ye ſee and feel his power? and if not, why do ye tremble, oh ye Inhabitants of the Earth? <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 99. 1. <hi>The Lord raigneth, let the people tremble, and let the Earth be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved;</hi> Ye finde it alſo in the Text, and that cloudy raigning there mentioned, or coming, is now, The Lord is entered his Throne upon Earth, but entered with clouds and darkneſs, and ſits there with clouds and darkneſs round about him; There is a three-fold appearing of this King upon Earth, for to be, firſt with Clouds, and that is now.</p>
            <p>Secondly, with his Spirit, and that is neer the pouring forth.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, with the brightneſs of his coming, 2. <hi>Theſſalon.</hi> 2. 8. <hi>Then ſhall that wicked be revealed, whom the Lord will conſume with the ſpirit of his mouth, and ſhall deſtroy with the brightneſs of his coming.</hi> And all theſe appearings will be in order, according to the order of God, and all of them deſtructive to the world, and to all things below God, and therefore the word Myſtery is brought in; The firſt appearing of this King upon the Throne, is ſuch a dark and cloudy appearing, that he is ſcarce known to be there, becauſe his firſt appearing and power is a cloudy appearing and power, but the ſecond will be more light becauſe ſpirituall, and therefore more deſtructive then the cloudy; And the third will be more excellent, more powerfull then both, becauſe it will bring along with it the perfect brightneſs of your King, and a perfect brightneſs of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſhining out to the view of all the world, which glory will not only conſume, but deſtroy all ſeeming glorious good and excellent things; I ſay, the firſt appearing of this King is ſo dark and cloudy, that it is hard to be known, whether he be come to ſit upon the throne of Judgment or no; and the reaſon why the Lord comes firſt with clouds, is, becauſe he taketh great delight to let his Iſrael know, firſt, of him, and where he is, whether in the place he ſpake of returning to, <hi>Hoſea,</hi> 5. 15. or whether riſen out of his holy ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117206:5"/> 
               <hi>Zecha.</hi> 2. 13. <hi>Be ſilent oh all fleſh before the Lord, for this my Lord the King is riſen up out of his holy habitation;</hi> and that the Lord lets ſome of his Iſrael know and underſtand where he is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther come down, or not come down, witneſs <hi>Noah, Geneſis</hi> 6. 13. witneſs <hi>Abraham, Geneſis</hi> 18. 17, 18. Witneſs <hi>Lot, Gen.</hi> 19. 12, 13. witneſs all the Prophets, and among the reſt, <hi>Huldah,</hi> 2 <hi>Cron.</hi> 34. 22. And witneſs <hi>Ezek.</hi> 4. 1. and 12. <hi>v.</hi> Witneſs <hi>Daniel, Dan.</hi> 10. 14. and 21. <hi>Now I come to make thee underſtand what is noted in the Scripture of truth.</hi> Witneſs the language of <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 4. <hi>But you bretheren are not in darkneſs, that that day ſhould take you as a thief;</hi> witneſs <hi>John,</hi> who ſaw by clouds the Lord coming to Judgment, and witneſs oh thou my ſoul, to the coming of Jeſus thy King, and long-lookt-for Lord and Saviour; but let me tell you one thing by the way, and that is this, the Lord hath yet Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers for to raiſe up, and to ſend forth, which Meſſengers mouths he will fill largely with good news, and that with great power too, and the news will be this (behold your King) <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 52. 7. But his appearing as yet is but a dark and cloudie appearing, ſo his Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers dark and cloudie Meſſengers; ſee what order there is in the goings of this King; look to it worldlings, and watch ye Saints, for the Lord my King is riſen out of his holy habitation, <hi>Jer.</hi> 25. 30, 33. <hi>The Lord ſhall roare from on high, and utter his voyce from his holy habitation,</hi> I muſt ſay the Lord <hi>does,</hi> the word <hi>ſhall</hi> is forgotten with my King, and the word <hi>does</hi> is come in the roome of it: therefore be ſilent oh all fleſh before the Lord; for he hath a controverſie with you all, and he is in this your day come downe to put an end to the controverſie, <hi>Jer.</hi> 30. A noyſe ſhall come even to the ends of the Earth, for the Lord hath a controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie with the nations, he will plead with all fleſh, and give them that are wicked to the Sword, and they ſhall paſs from end to end: why, the noyſe is come, and the controverſie is in diſpute: what, do not ye hear the voice of God? he calleth to you all, not one is except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that is this day in the world, and the voice is, Hear oh ye Prieſt, and hearken ye houſe of the Kings, and give ear oh ye houſe of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 5. 1. Here is Kings, Prieſts, and Iſrael, I muſt put in one number more; that is, all ye people of the world, becauſe the Lord is come to end his controverſie with all fleſh, therefore not one ſhall eſcape, no, not Kings, and for you oh Emperors, Kings, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117206:5"/> Rulers, and Princes of the earth; I muſt tell you one ſad thing, you and your names are dying, and your Crowns are taking off from your heads throughout the world, and the Saints King, Jeſus by name, the ancient of dayes, Son, the Lord of Hoſts, righteous Branch, he ſhall be ſet up King in your rooms. And thats the reaſon why he is coming now with clouds, and it will not be long ere all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the world be broken down, nay, they are in this your day ruining by the King of Kings. <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. 44. In the day of theſe Kings ſhall the God of heaven ſet up a Kingdom, which ſhal break in pieces all other Kingdoms; Where do you think to ſtand, O wordlings! who have made gods of earthly Kings, ye and your gods are fallen, like the Philiſtims falſe gods, and ſhall never be remembred more<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I muſt confeſs with you, God by his own providence ſuffered Kings in the earth for to be, and cauſed them there for to reign, but now their reign is almoſt up, and their glory is almoſt at an end, and when it is not almoſt, but altogether up, then the Lord will do to you, as he did to <hi>Nebucadnezar;</hi> let me tell you, O Kings, you are all weighed in the ballance of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi> and being weighed, you are found too light, and I hear a voice from the Lord, ſaying to you all, as the Lord ſaid to <hi>Belſhazer, The Kingdoms are departing from you,</hi> and are to be divided among them, who are more fit to reign then you a great deal, this a myſtery to you, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. 31. <hi>Dan</hi> 5. 20. The Lord is come to unthrone you all, O Kings! and that is the judgment of the Lord upon you in this your day, but doth that he doth, after a cloudy manner, that you cannot underſtand nor ſee, and therefore you contend for your Crown ſtill, but the Lord will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer you, and therefore is he riſen to unthroan all, <hi>Haggai.</hi> 2. 22. <hi>I will overthrow the Throan of Kingdoms, and bring down the power of Nations, and their riders ſhall come down every one by the ſword of his brother;</hi> Take notice how they ſhall come down, and ſee if the Lord be not riſen to pull down all powers; hear again what the Lord ſaith, and in his word manifeſts that he regards no power, but that that is righteous and juſt, like himſelf, and if they be not ſo, he will unthroan them all, and therefore it is he is come, <hi>Eze.</hi> 21. 25. <hi>your day is come, all ye Rulers of the earth, in the which your iniquity ſhall have an end, therefore thus ſaith the Lord, remove the Diadem, take off the Crown, this ſhall not be the ſame, exalt him that is low, and abaſe him that is high, for I will overturn, overturn, overturn, and it ſhall be no</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:117206:6"/> 
               <hi>more untill he come, whoſe right all is.</hi> Let me tell you all that are in power, let it be kingly, or not kingly, you ſhall all be overturned, and for the <hi>Kings</hi> of the earth, if they were once as the ſignet upon the Lords right hand, yet now their time is come of being pluckt from thence: Oh how all the world ſtartles at the footſteps of the Lord upon earth, being they are cloudy, dark, bloody, and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous ſteps; indeed well ye may fear, when the Lord appears ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with clouds and tempeſts; who is he that will not fear, and be in great trouble in that day? why this is the day, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 3. Our God is come, ye muſt now reade it; the <hi>verſe</hi> indeed runs <hi>Our God ſhall come and ſhall not keep ſilence, a fire ſhall devoure before him, and it ſhall be tempeſtuous round about him. Eſay</hi> 30. 30. <hi>The Lord ſhall cauſe his glorious voyce to be heard, and ſhall ſhew the light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning down of his arm, with indignation of his anger, with the flames of devouring fire, ſcattering hail-ſtones and tempeſts:</hi> you know clouds are the forerunners of ſtorms and tempeſts; and this the cloudy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of the Lord hath cauſed for to be, great ſtorms, and amongſt many, one is this, the ſtorm of war, <hi>Eſay</hi> 3. 25. <hi>Thy men ſhall fall by the ſword, and thy mighty in the war,</hi> Is it not thus? let me tell you, the war that is now in the world, is the war that Chriſt ſpake of long ago, and that was the war of wars, though not the firſt, yet the laſt war, and that war is the confuſed, and unnaturall war, a war ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving many diviſions in it, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 51, 52<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 53<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> here is diviſion upon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, the father and the ſon, the mother and the daughter, each one againſt the other, and a war that cauſeth moſt to be offended; <hi>Matt.</hi> 24. 10. Then ſhall many be offended and betray one another, and hate one another, it is an iniquity-abounding war, <hi>verſe</hi> 12. great tribulation attending of it, <hi>verſ.</hi> 21. This ſhall be in the day of the Son of man; how is it, that ye do not diſcern this time? you ſhall hear of wars, ſaith Chriſt, but not only kingdom againſt kingdom, but kingdoms divided, Cities, Towns, and Families divided, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions in every mans heart too, as well as in the kingdoms. Hear all once more, The Lord is come down with a ſword in his hand, which ſword hath a long time been bathed in heaven, and now it is fallen upon every accurſed thing, or upon the people of his Curſe. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 34. 5. Come near O Nations, and hear, <hi>Kings, Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> and thou <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for you are all turned out of the way, and now the Lord hath met with you; look how every man comes bleeding back, ſome die in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117206:6"/> the place where the Lord met them, and ſome falne by the way in their retreat; We have all turned aſide from the Lord, and therefore wo be unto us, <hi>Eſay</hi> 10. 1, 2, 3, 4. <hi>Wo be unto them that decree unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous decrees, and turn aſide the needy from judgment, and take away the right from the poor, that widows may be their prey;</hi> O how is this Scripture fulfilled in this our age, therefore all our glory is like to come down, nay, it is falling, it is falling<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it is falling, for the Sword is drawn; I muſt call it the Sword of the Lord, the Lords ſacrificing Sword, which will not regard, neither <hi>Kings, Prieſts,</hi> nor <hi>People,</hi> becauſe all are falne from the Lord, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6. 13. For from the leaſt of them to the greateſt, from the People even unto the Prieſt, all are given unto covetouſneſs; <hi>Iſrael,</hi> thou art not out of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, the Lord hath a controverſie with you among the reſt, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4. 1, 2, 3. Hear the word of the Lord, ye are all unclean, and a pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted generation, fit for nothing but to fall by the Sword of the Lord, and to be devoured by the fire of his jealouſie, not regarding <hi>Kings. Ezec.</hi> 39. 18. Ye ſhall eat the fleſh of the mighty, and drink the blood of the Princes of the earth, every one hath taken of the accurſed thing, and every one ſhall drink of the bloud which his bathed Sword lets out, and therefore the Lord hath called for a Sword, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 13. 3. <hi>I have commanded my ſanctified ones, I have called my mighty ones for my anger; verſ.</hi> 11. He will puniſh for iniquity, and cauſe the proud to ceaſe; <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. The Lord will make a man more precious then the fine gold: behold this is the day, the Sword of the Lords vengeance is come down in this the day of the Lords vengeance, and in the year of the recompence of the controverſie of <hi>Sion,</hi> therefore behold the day of the Lord God of Hoaſts, the day of his vengance, a day of wrath, a day of trouble, of diſtreſs, of waſtings, of clouds, of thick darkneſs that no man knows where he is, for every man walks up and down like blind men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; that is the reaſon that every man runs upon the ſword of his brother, friends: All things, and all powers, and all practiſes are corrupt, and perfectly corrupt, and this cloudy power is to deſtroy them, and now being come deſtroy he will, and that Nations, not a few, and for that end the Lord hath called for a Sword, and this Sword ſhall enter into all the inhabitable parts of the earth. Me thinks I ſee, where the Lord hath called up his ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ones, and I hear him ſtill calling them up in all the kingdoms of the world, and ere long you ſhall hear of the Sword of the Lord
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117206:7"/> being drawn, and ſheathed in the ſides of all Kingdoms by a civill war; <hi>England,</hi> thou haſt begun to drink blood, and thou ſhalt yet drink one draught more to all the world, and they ſhall pledge thee round in a bowl of blood again, for the Lord will give them all blood to drink; therefore Hear all ye ſanctified ones of the Lord, whom he hath called up to offer up a ſacrifice of blood, in what Nation, or Kingdom ſo ever you are, <hi>Eſay</hi> 13. 3. <hi>Eſay</hi> 54. 16. The Lord hath created you for to deſtroy, and called you to do that, that never was done, and to unthroan that never was unthroaned throughout the world, yea, and that quickly. <hi>Jer.</hi> 25. 26. And all the Kings of the North far and neer, one with another, and all the kingdoms of the world which are upon the face of the earth; wherefore look now on your left ſide, for there, I ſuppoſe is a ſword, it is the Lords bathed ſword, his ſacrificing ſword, the ſword of the Lords vengance; turn you whether you will, ye ſhall never be prevailed againſt, ſo as to be conquered by a ſword of ſteel of the world, you ſhall have power to conquer all, and ſo to overturn all, and to break down all powers, wayes, and governments; but let me tell you one thing, you ſhall never have power to ſettle any thing, for ye have not wiſdom enough, nor is it any of your work; that is the Lords: do you yours, and let the Lord alone with his, and take heed of abuſing your power, and corrupting of it with injuſtice, if you do, God will raiſe up a more refined power then yours, and more juſt, and conquer you, who have been conquerors, and ſend you to your graves in blood; for this is the bloody age, and when you are gone, the Lord my King will ariſe, and by his glorious light conquer the moſt juſt and moſt refined conquerers, and ſo you ſhall all fall, by the Sword of the Lord, and the laſt power by the light of the ſome Lord, in the day of the Lords ſpiritual and light appearing; This is the cloudy day of the Lord, and the day in which he judges men by the ſword, and therefore it is no more mans, but the Lords, <hi>Jer.</hi> 12. 12 <hi>The Spoylers are come up upon all high places, and the ſword of the Lord ſhall devoure from one end of the world to the other, and no fleſh ſhall have peace.</hi> A ſecond reaſon why the Lord comes with clouds, and blood, is this, becauſe his feet ſtand upon a place where much blood hath been ſpilt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. 6. <hi>I ſaw the woman drunken with the blood of the Saints, and with the blood of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs of Jeſus;</hi> You Kings and Rulers of the Earth, you have ſpilt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117206:7"/> the blood of the Saints by your Law throughout the world, And the Lord my King is come down to follow you throughout the world again, for to give you a deadly draught, and to avenge the blood of his Saints, and ſo give you blood for blood, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8. 6. In the cup which ſhe hath filled, fill to her the double, to her utter ruine and perfect removing, 14. <hi>ver.</hi> and <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. 6. Oh nations! the cup of the fierceneſs of the wrath of God is put into your hand by my King, and I cannot but tell you of it, You have drunke blood, oh Kings, for many an Age, and now the Age is up, and time fulfilled, and you ſhall drink blood again oh Rulers, and all people, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 49. 25. <hi>I will contend with them that contend with thee, I will feed them that oppreſs thee with their own fleſh, and they ſhall be drunken with their own blood,</hi> let me tell you oh Kings, and all ye Rulers of the earth, from the firſt day ye wore a Crown, and had power put into your hand, even unto this my day, you have all along ſlain better then your ſelves, and each one of them reſembled the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a King, and now the Lord is come with Clouds to make inquiry who they were you ſlew, you have the type in <hi>Judges</hi> 8. 18. <hi>Then ſaid he unto</hi> Zeba <hi>and</hi> Zalmunna, <hi>What manner of men were they whom you ſlew at</hi> Tabor? <hi>And they anſwered, as thou art, ſo were they, each one reſembling the perſon of a King; They were my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, even the ſons of my mother, hadſt thou ſaved them; I would not have ſlain you.</hi> Here is a myſterie, but now the time of ſlaying is come, ſlay I muſt, This is the diſpenſation of the Lord through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the world, and all this ariſeth from the Lords being Generall of all Armyes, which are ſanctified by him for this work, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 11, 12, 13. <hi>v. And he was cloathed in a veſture dipt in blood;</hi> ye have great trouble in the Earth, and all ariſeth this day from the Lords being come with clouds, and by reaſon of his cloudie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all Councels are darkned, and all powers are broken down, let them be powers temporall or ſpirituall, as you call them, and therefore the Lord hath it mentioned three times, overturn, overturn, overturn, untill he come whoſe right it is, and he will give it him: indeed it is my happineſs that the Lord will do this; for by this I know, I ſhall in due time be perfect, as my heavenly Father is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, but for the preſent, there is nothing in my heart, nor in the world, but that that is fit for ruine, for truth is fallen in the ſtreet, equity cannot enter into her kingdom, nor the heart; worldly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117206:8"/> wiſdome is turned to folly, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 29. 14. Spirituall and heavenly wiſdome, that is returned into the Fathers boſome, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 41. 28. There is not a man, no not yet a Counſellor among you all, that is able to anſwer the Lord a word, if he ſhould ask you, out of the Cloud, what you are doing, for he hath taken away all wiſdome from you; <hi>Is wiſdome no more? is Councell periſhed from the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent? is their wiſdome vaniſhed? Jer.</hi> 49. 7. Yes, the Lord hath deſtroyed all the wiſe men of the world, or elſe turned their wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome into fooliſhneſs, <hi>Obadiah</hi> 8. <hi>verſe. Shall I not in that day deſtroy the wiſe men, and the underſtanding men?</hi> In what day, oh Lord my King? why, in my cloudy day, in a day which I come to recompenſe, with an overturning all, and making the earth empty, and in turning all out of the world that is in it, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 24. 1. I will make the earth empty, make it waſte, and turne it upſide down, Oh! what haſte the Lord maketh to finiſh his work in the world, my King turneth and turneth, removeth and ſcattereth, and yet not a man takes notice of it, and I beholding my father, cannot but ſpeak to you, and therefore awake oh ſoules, for me thinks I hear Iſrael begin to ſing in this the cloudy day of God, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 24. 14. <hi>They ſhall lift up their voice, and ſhall ſing for the Majeſtie of the Lord, and ſhall cry aloud from the Sea;</hi> but for thee oh world, wiſdome and underſtanding hath left thee, and the Lord hath befooled all thy Counſels, and put a ſpirit of fear into the heart of every man, and whatſoever men do, they do in fear and much trouble, for this is the fearfull Age; Hath not the Lord ſcattered all power? being but corrupted, tyrannicall, beaſtly power, ſo that there is no way left to ſave the kingdomes of the world, no, nor thee oh <hi>England,</hi> but by another manner of power, thou dreameſt of, but I ſee; for that way, by which the Lord once ſaved kingdomes, is now become the only way to ruine king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes; And by this you may ſee that this cloudie appearing of my Lord, hath turned the world upſide down, this is the Lords un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throning day, it is the <hi>Worlds-power-changing</hi> day, and it is a <hi>fleſh-ruining</hi> day, and for this end the Lord is come out of his place with clouds, for to puniſh the Inhabitants of the earth, for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity, and to cauſe it to diſcloſe its blood, and therefore it ſhall no more cover the ſlain, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 26. 21. At this Scripture in his fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, even in this our day, the earth ſhakes and trembles, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. 7.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117206:8"/> He hath made great diviſions in the world, great commotions there are, troubles and fears, ſhakings and tremblings, hearts-fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and faith-dying, the whole land is barren of faith, the way of truth is hid; Wit, that hath hid it ſelfe, and underſtanding hath withdrawn it ſelf, into its ſecret chamber indeed, it is ſought of many, but not found; for unrighteouſneſs, and unconſtancy proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth upon earth; Friends, the world is grown very weak, by reaſon of age, and therefore needs muſt the evils be very great that are upon it, I, and ſo they are, for my heart can ſay Amen to this evill world; Theſe are the evill dayes, the perilous dayes, the ſin-multiplying dayes, dayes, in which the word <hi>(do violence to no man</hi> is forgotten) and for love in the ſpirit, it cannot be found in neither kingdome, nor heart. Judgment and Juſtice, with all the other righteous ſtreames is departed, and run ſarre away, from Kings, Princes, Rulers, Judges, Magiſtrates, Prieſts, people, and from thee oh <hi>Iſrael</hi> too, and therefore the Lord is come down to deſtroy all, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7. 28. Oh <hi>England, thou art the nation of all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that obeyeth not the voice of the Lord, Iſa.</hi> 59 3, 4. and ſo along to the 15. <hi>ver. Your hands, oh people, throughout the Land are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed with blood, your fingers with iniquity, your lips ſpeak nothing but lies;</hi> not a man in thee oh <hi>England</hi> acts in a juſt way, not any plead for truth, The way of peace ye know not, there is no Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in your goings, ye grope like blinde men, and are in deſolate places, as dead men, ſin and iniquity is grown almoſt to the height in thee oh Land, and therefore now behold the Lord, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59. 16, 17. <hi>I ſaw, and there was no man, and therefore behold, I the Lord will put on righteouſneſs as a breaſt plate, with ſalvation and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, for to repay every man;</hi> Ye have loſt all, oh ye Kings, and Rulers, people, and Miniſters of all Lands; for Goſpel-light and truth, is taken away by the Lord from you, as well as judgment, juſtice, and righteouſneſs from Kings, and Rulers, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 29. 10, 11. <hi>The viſion of all is become unto you as a book ſealed;</hi> Hear oh ye Miniſters! your gifts are periſhed, and quite blaſted, and your ſheep are ſcattered, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4. 6. Think what you will, your gifts are periſhed, although you may ſay, it is not ſo, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18. 18. Ye and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> gifts are loſt, and the judgment of the Lord is upon you, as well as upon <hi>Kings</hi> and Rulers, for the night of darkneſs which the Lord ſpake of long agoe, is fallen upon you all, and darkneſs
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117206:9"/> hath covered you all, even thick darkneſs, <hi>Micah</hi> 3. 6, 7. <hi>Here is miſchief upon miſchief</hi> to the purpoſe, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7. 26. <hi>Kings,</hi> Prieſts, and people, and thou oh <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ye are all turned backward; The wiſe men ſhall be turned backward, ſo that the way of truth, and Goſpel-light is hid from you all, your condition hath been a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing condition many hundred years, <hi>Prov.</hi> 29 18. <hi>Where there is no viſion the people periſh,</hi> The word of the Lord is a precious thing; and it is grown very precious amongſt us; Ruling in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is very precious, Magiſtracy according to the order of God is very precious too, for I know not where it is; There is a perfect loſſe of all Iuſtice and Iudgment, righteouſneſs and truth, there is a famine upon you all; <hi>Kings</hi> and Rulers they are famiſhed, and loſt in their judgment, Miniſters and people they are famiſhed too, for the Goſpel-knowledg of the Lord, which is bread indeed, is taken by the Lord from you all, yea, and my very pen ſpeaks out to you all, that I am one, whoſe ſoul is half famiſhed for want of bread, what a cloudy day are we in? it is no wonder to me to ſee the Lord come now with Clouds to overturn all, becauſe all is grown corrupt, and fit for nothing elſe, for the wiſdome of both <hi>Kings,</hi> Prieſts, and people, and thou oh <hi>Iſrael,</hi> is all turned into folly, our knowledg into ignorance, and our light into darkneſs, and our peace into trouble, &amp; this is by reaſon of the Lords being come down for to fight againſt all Nations, and all things, and to plead with all fleſh, for with fire and with ſword the Lord is now pleading with all fleſh, and the ſlain of the Lord are many, and ſhall be more, and the Lord is gathering all together for that end, <hi>Zepha.</hi> 3. 8. O world! me thinks I hear a rumor from my Lord, and I ſee, an Embaſſadour which is ſent from the Lord to all the world, to tell them they muſt gather themſelves together for ruine, <hi>Eſay</hi> 24. 22. <hi>And they ſhall be gathered together as priſoners are gathered together,</hi> Who? why Kings, and the hoſt of the high ones, that are on high; The dayes in which we live are the Lords gathering dayes, <hi>Joel</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. The Lord does gather, and that round the world, and all Ploughſhares are a beating into ſwords, and Pruning-hooks into ſpears, and you will ſee all kingdoms watered with blood ere long, clouds full of blood, and ſea full of blood, and the whole world full of blood too, and a man ſhall come to be more precious then the golden wedge of <hi>Ophire;</hi> therefore you that are for the ſword, and you that are for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117206:9"/> the famine, to the famine, and you that are for the peſtilence, to the peſtilence, for this is the great day of the Lord, his dividing day, his cloudy dividing day, his cloudy gathering day, and his cloudy ruining day: your day is come, O worldlings! and now fall you muſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for you are but the left hand hoaſt of God; the Lord hath two great hoſts, that have lived together many a day, let them alone till the harveſt, ſaith Chriſt; now the harveſt is ready, and therefore ye begin to fall; <hi>I ſaw the hoaſt of heaven,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22. 29. Here is two hoaſts, and theſe are called multitudes, <hi>Joel</hi> 3. 14. And theſe multitudes are gathered together by the Lord into the valley of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſaphat;</hi> and by reaſon of the multitudes, it is turned into a valley, deciſion, all the world is turned into <hi>Jehoſaphats</hi> valley, or into a valley of deciſion in the world; nay it is, for the Lord is come, and by his cloudy appearing, hath made a great diviſion in the world. Thy <hi>King,</hi> O <hi>Sion</hi> is come, and the end of his coming is, to take thee from the enemies, and the enemies from thee, and the world from both, and when this old world is gone, thy kingdom and glory is gone, O worldling! the Lord is making great haſt to remove you, and for that end he is gathering you, <hi>Ezeck</hi> 38. 14, 15, 16. In theſe <hi>verſes</hi> they gather, <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. the Lord riſes up, at <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. they ſhake at his riſing, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> alſo, and they fall in <hi>Ezeck.</hi> 39. 4. Thou maiſt read thy doom here O worldling! ye are in gathering by the Lord, and ye are, and ſhall be ſlain by the Lord, and his <hi>Iſrael,</hi> do, and ſhall go away conquerers, and ſing praiſes to their <hi>King,</hi> who hath taken to himſelf his great power, and reigns, although it be but with clouds, and as his coming is a cloudy coming, ſo his wrath that he poures forth is a cloudy wrath; the day of the Lords wrath is come, and yet ſtill to come, and it haſteth greatly, thou haſt outward tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall wrath falne upon thee from the Lord, and therefore ye are intombed in your own blood; the Lord hath waited long upon the world, for their filling up the meaſures of their fathers wrath, and now they are full; the world is full of evill and darkneſs, hands full, and minds full, and hearts full, and now behold he is come to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence wickedneſs filled up to the brim, with plagues filled up to the brim, and my <hi>King</hi> hath begun with the plague of the ſword, called by the name of a Sicle, <hi>Joel</hi> 3. 13. and in <hi>verſe</hi> 9. <hi>A Sword;</hi> you wonder a at theſe ſtrange things that befall you, and you ſay in your trouble, you think the world is almoſt at an end; why, thy
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117206:10"/> world, O worlding! is almoſt at an end, it ſhakes mightily, it reels a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pace, and would quickly fall, were but thy doom read to thee; you ſhall receive your doom here, and ſentence in this world, where you have paſſed ſentence upon ſo many of the Lords heritage; thy ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence hath been upon them, <hi>Let them die the death, Pſal.</hi> 94. 21. They gathered themſelves together againſt the ſouls of the righteous, and condemned the innocent blood; the very ſame ſentence is paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon thee from the Lord with a wo, <hi>Eſay</hi> 33. 1. <hi>Wo to thee that ſpoileſt and waſt not ſpoiled.</hi> and <hi>Eſay</hi> 54. 17. wo be to you indeed, for you have riſen up againſt the Lords heritage, and now the Lord is riſen up againſt you; you have judged the Fathers beloved many thouſand years, and he is now come for to judg you; and the firſt Judgment is this, a wounding you all with a taking peace, reſt, and quietneſs from you, and ſo taking, that you ſhall never ſee it more, becauſe the day of the Lord is come, the day which thou haſt ſo long deſired, with a praying Thy kingdom come, Thy will be done, and Hallowed be thy Name; thou mayſt now, it may be, call to minde what you have ſaid all of you, and whom you are angry with: how many times have you ſaid, Hallowed by thy Name, Thy kingdom come? you little know what you ſaid, and what you deſired; you prayed for the Lord to come and glorifie his name, which you, and I, and all the world have prophaned all our dayes; and you prayed for the Lords Power, Juſtice, and Judgments to fall upon you; behold it is come according to your deſire, although it be with clouds, and that is the reaſon why Kings fall, and loſe their Crowns and Thrones too; the Lord, the Lord of hoaſts my King, whoſe poſſeſſion all the kingdoms are, is come, and earthly Kings have, do, and ſhall perfectly fall before him, for all kingdoms are the Lords, and he is now come for to take poſſeſſion of them, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. 13, 14. <hi>Behold one like the ſon of man came with the clouds of heaven, and came to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient of dayes, and there was given to him dominion, glory, and a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> what wilt thou do, O world? now thy long deſire is granted, or where will ye ſtand, the Saints fear, and are ſo moved, they cannot tell where to ſtand: <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 2. But who may abide the day of his coming, and who ſhall ſtand when he appeareth? Behold he is come, and you are doubly miſerable by it, and in a worſe condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then ever you were, for there went out a wo againſt you long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go for this thy deſire, <hi>Amos</hi> 5. 18. Wo unto you that deſire the day
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117206:10"/> of the Lord, for the day of the Lord is darkneſs and not light, even very dark, and no brightneſs in it, therefore what profit haſt thou by it, but rather trouble, fear, with great aſtoniſhments, and ſorrow added, and in ſtead of a Lyon, a Lyon and a Bear, and a Serpent too, for to bite, and to tear, and who ſhall deliver you out of his hand? you are hurt, and in trouble, and yet you cannot tell who hurt you; why, it is the Lord, and nothing but the Lord, and he is come for to gather you for deſtruction; the day of the Lords gathering is the day of the worlds reeling too and fro, <hi>Eſay</hi> 24. 19. <hi>The earth reels too and fro</hi> (I muſt reade it) <hi>and is removing like a Cottage, and the tranſgreſſions thereof are heavie upon it, and ſhall fall and never riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain;</hi> there are great breakings up and great cries in <hi>verſe</hi> 11. and the 21. the Lord puniſhes, the Lord is riſen to the pray, do you not hear the ſound of his feet? nay, ye do not only hear, but feel, not only feel but ſee: and yet ye cannot tell that the Lord is come down, and that is your plague, <hi>Mich.</hi> 1. 3. Behold the Lord cometh forth out of his place, and will come down and tread upon the high places of the earth, and the mountains ſhall be moulten under him; you are all in great trouble and in fear, and you would fain know what the meaning of it is, and to what it will grow; thus much is the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of all your trouble, it telleth you, the Lord, and <hi>Sions King</hi> is come down upon the earth, and by reaſon of his preſence the earth ſhakes, and fears and trembles, I, and ſinks under him, being not able to bear his weight, nor to behold his cloudy preſence; indeed it is impoſſible but that it ſhould fear, for the breaker up is come up, and hath broke up. <hi>Mich.</hi> 2. 13. And <hi>Michael</hi> the Prince ſtands up, and my Lord is riſen, and your <hi>King</hi> is before you, O Saints, this is a myſtery, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 1. And there is now come, and for to come ſtill, ſuch a time of trouble as never was, for that muſt be ſhaken, ye, and is ſhaking that never was ſhaken, and that muſt be removed that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was removed, becauſe that that is to be brought to my Father, is that that never yet was brought; heaven and earth muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved before thy glory ſhall come to thee, O <hi>Iſrael!</hi> Oh how hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth does ſhake, at this the cloudy appearing of Jeſus Chriſt. Friends, where are you all, where do you now ſtand? in this the day of the Lords ſhaking heaven and earth; let me tell you one thing in a myſtery, again, all are riſen out of their ſeat in heaven, becauſe of the great ſhaking there, and all are riſen out of their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117206:11"/> ſeat on earth, and dare not ſit any longer there, becauſe of the great ſhaking there; <hi>Behold I ſhake heaven and earth, ſea, and dry land, all Nations, and then the deſire of all Nations ſhall come and fill ye all, O ye Iſrael, with his glory, Hag.</hi> 2. 6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 26. Oh what a ſhaking is there of both things viſible and inviſible! there is a leaving ſtrong holds viſible, and a leaving ſtrong holds inviſible, let me tell you one thing more, the ſhaking of heaven and of earth is ſo great, that the <hi>Sion</hi> of God, for whoſe ſake all this is, are but as when a ſtandard-bearer fainteth, and for their ſakes theſe dayes ſhall be ſhortned, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10. 17, 18. Oh what fear and trembling is there ſeiſed upon the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of all the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, who is able to behold his cloudy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence! <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3. 16. When I heard, my belly trembled, my lips quivered at the voyce, rottenneſſe entered into my bones, I trembled in my ſelf I, that I might reſt in the day of trouble; when he cometh up unto the people, he will invade them with his troops, The Lord in this our day is invading all lands, and his coming is with clouds; chuſe whether ye will believe it or no, and this his cloudy power, hath, and will all fall upon powers, let them be powers Kingly, or powers Parliamentary, or power by Sword, ye muſt all fall, but the power of the ſword ſhal be the laſt that ſhal be deſtroyed, I mean the laſt viſible power: this cloudy power of the Lord is falne upon all your Idols, temporall and ſpirituall; and high time it is, for all lands are full of Idols, and every man boweth to them, <hi>Eſay</hi> 2. 8. 9. The lofty look of man ſhall be humbled, and the Lord alone ſhall be exalted, and ye ſhall caſt away your Idols of ſilver and gold, and hide your ſelves, if you could tell where, for fear of the Lord, and for the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his Majeſty: This day is the day of the Lord, and yet alas, ye are all ſo blinde, that ye look for peace, and what have you for to do with peace, are not ye all of the earth? have ye not all a wicked earthly minde, and an evil idolatrous heart, and an earthly god, called the god of this world? which god of this world hath blinded your eyes, that ye cannot tell what the Lord is doing; ye look for peace, and that is taken from the earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. 4. <hi>And there went out another horſe that was red, and power was given to him that ſate thereon to take peace from the earth and that they ſhould kill one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and there was given unto him a great ſword: England,</hi> what ſaiſt thou to this, and now therefore behold trouble, and trouble is moſt fitteſt for you all; O world! thou haſt been a troubler of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117206:11"/> the Lords heritage; and O <hi>Iſrael!</hi> thou haſt been a troubler of thy Father, and that made him return to his own place: thou O world! haſt been a wonder unto death, the fathers beloved, in ſtead of pleading their cauſe, and now the Lord is come to plead the cauſe of his heritage himſelf, and for thee, O <hi>Iſrael!</hi> thy life hath been ſo wicked, and ſo grieving to the Spirit of God, ſo that thy long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in this thy ſpirit-grieving way, hath wounded thy King to death in thee, and the life which thou now liveſt is a dead life; wounded, I ſay, thou haſt thy dear Lord, <hi>Zach.</hi> 13. 6. <hi>What are theſe wounds in thy hand? theſe are the wounds which were given me in the houſe of my friend, Zach.</hi> 12. 10. The world hath wounded Chriſt, and his members have wounded him, and behold now the Lord is riſen and come down, for to wound, and never heal, and yet for to wound and to heal, that is, for to pull down and to build, to pull down and to deſtroy all, both Kings; Prieſts, People, and thee O <hi>Iſrael!</hi> and to take away from us that which we are very loath for to loſe, but loſe it we muſt, being got into the cloudy day of God, and if <hi>Noah, Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Iob</hi> were in theſe our dayes, they ſhould ſave but their own ſouls, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14. 17. and 21. <hi>verſ.</hi> Behold the Lord is come, do not ye hear his ſound yet? how long ſhall the Trumpet blow, O ſleepers! ere ye will awake? the Lord is come down, and walks up and down the earth, and not a man heareth him, or ſeeth him: this is a myſtery, ye are certainly aſleep, O ſouls! <hi>Kings, Prieſts, People,</hi> yea and <hi>Iſrael</hi> too, and that lulled aſleep by the Devill into a heart-ſleep, and when the heart is once aſleep, the cloudy appearing of Jeſus Chriſt cannot awaken it, and a heart-ſleep is within one ſtep of the ſleep of eternall death, and if ye lie a little longer, O all ye people of the world! <hi>Lord have mercy upon you,</hi> may be written upon all your doors, for my <hi>King</hi> will paſs by, and enter into his Fathers kingdom, with all his Princes, and then for to awake will be too late; what not yet? cannot ye behold my <hi>King,</hi> nor ſee him? why, you ſhall, for the clouds ſhall be taken away, and therefore the words run with <hi>every eye ſhall ſee him,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>And every eye ſhall ſee him.</q>
            <p>The ſecond appearing of my <hi>King</hi> will be a ſpirituall appearing, and ſo a ſpirituall deſtruction ſhall attend this ſpirituall appearing,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117206:12"/> that is, a deſtruction attended with much light, therefore the word <hi>Every eye</hi> is brought in; when this cloudy appearing of Jeſus Chriſt is finiſhed, then comes this ſpiritual appearing of the Lord for to deſtroy that the cloudy appearing of my <hi>King</hi> could not do, which ſpirituall appearing will cauſe all fleſh for to tremble doubly, and out of trembling, fear, and out of fear, flie to the mountains, hills, and great rocks for to hide themſelves from the preſence of the Lord, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. 16, 17. But let me tell you, there will not be a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain nor a hill left in all the world to hide thee from the preſence of the Lord, for that is the reaſon why the Lord comes firſt with clouds and darkneſs to remove every mountain and hill, and every hiding place, that you ſhall have no where to go for ſhelter, for the Lord will make bare his holy arm in the eyes of all the Nations, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52. 10. Oh what an exceeding light, and glorious appearing of Jeſus Chriſt will there be ere long, for all eyes ſhall ſee, and light ſhall burn, and God will ſearch all the world, and all hearts too, and cauſe them for to ſee and know what they are, <hi>Iſa</hi> 9. 5. Every battle of the Warrier is with a confuſed noiſe, and garments rouled in blood. This ſhall be with burning and fury of fire. <hi>And Zeph.</hi> 1. 12. <hi>at that time I will ſearch Jeruſalem with candles, and puniſh the men that are ſetled upon their lees, and ſay in their heart, the Lord will not do good, neither will he do evill;</hi> but you ſhall know ere long, what the Lord will do when he cometh, for to give you eyes to ſee withall, that you never ſaw; there are divers eyes, the eyes of the body, the eye of Reaſon, the eye of Faith, and the eye of the Underſtanding; for the eye of the body, you know it is a dim-ſighted thing, and cannot behold the Sun, it is good for nothing but for to give light unto the body; but this eye here ſpoken of by <hi>John</hi> is a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall eye, or ye may call it the eye of the Lord gone forth from the Lord to the works of his hands to behold their great Workman, the Lord of hoſts, for nothing can behold the Lord but that which comes from the Lord: I am apt to think, that the eye which the Lord will open to all fleſh, in the day of his glorious light appearing, will be the eye of the Underſtanding and my reaſon is this, becauſe that <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that by that eye when once opened, they ſhall know what is the hope of their calling, what is the riches of his glory of his inheritance in his Saints. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 18. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41. 20. That we may ſee, know, and underſtand together, and then ſhall they ſee eye to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117206:12"/> eye, when the Lord ſhall bring again <hi>Sion,</hi> and then ſhall we behold him as he is. Hear <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ye gentile world too, for ye are both brought in; hear <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the firſt ſight that thou ſhalt have of thy King, will be a ſad ſight, for thy wounded Saviour will be repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto thee, which thou haſt wounded, pierced, and grieved all thy days; but the time now of thy grieving him is almoſt up, and he is coming out of cloudy diſpenſations, for to cauſe thee by his light to ſee, what thou art, and what thou haſt done, and what a condition thou art in; and when he hath carried thee, hither and thither, up and down, here and there, and ſhewed thee all thy abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations and all thy idols, and imaginary religious Exerciſes, as he did to <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and in the Temple there, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 8. 5, 6, 9, 10, 11. and ſo to the end of the Chapter; that is a Goſpel type, we may read there what our condition is; for thou art the Temple of God, and this Temple of the Lord is defiled with all maner of unclean things. O thou Temple of the Lord! there is great abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in thee, ſpiritual abomination, myſterious abominations, and there dwells in thee, thou canſt not tell what; for every thing that bears not the image of the Lord, is ſin upon thee, and thou art de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed with all maner of unclean things; with an unclean heart, an unclean minde, an unclean converſation. O how death is written upon all thy labors and ways, rathen then life: Behold therefore the Lord is come down for to open an eye to thee, wherewith thou ſhalt ſee all that thou haſt done, to be wicked, fleſhly, and nought: The firſt ſight will be a ſorrowful ſight, but after ſorrow comes joy. <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the Lord will firſt open thy eye, becauſe judgment ſhall begin firſt with thee, yea, this ſpiritual judgment: The Lord will firſt ſearch thee with candles, and after thee, then thy enemies; thou ſhalt ſee firſt, becauſe thou ſhalt riſe firſt; nay, doſt not thou begin to ſee? for methinks the clouds begin to break; if not, what's the reaſon of ſo much ſtrange noyſes among the <hi>Sion</hi> of God? was there ever heard or ſeen the like, that is in this our age? what diſtreſs? what blaſphemies? what curſings? Theſe days are the laſt days, theſe days are the blaſpheming days: I tremble to think how all the world is, and will be filled with blaſphemy, <hi>Revel.</hi> 13. 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7. 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16. 9, 11, 21. Here is trouble indeed to the purpoſe, war was but the beginning; and this ſhall be the end, and when ended, never trouble more ſhall come neer thee, O <hi>Iſrael;</hi> for thou ſhalt ſee thy
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117206:13"/> King ere long with great joy, and with ſuch a beholding of him, as thou never yet didſt behold him withall, and by this thy beholding of him, thou ſhalt goe forth and ſpeak great things of his name to the conſuming of all the world, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 40. 3. <hi>And he ſhall put a new ſong into thy mouth (even praiſe unto our God) men ſhall ſee it and fear,</hi> God will come and conſume all within thee, becauſe thou ſhalt conſume all without thee, and make all fall before thee, by the light and glory that God will cloath upon thee, and all ſhall come unto thee, in chaines, and ſhall bow, and make ſupplication unto thee, and <hi>Pſ.</hi> 149. 8. <hi>To binde their Kings in Chaines,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2 8. <hi>Whom he will conſume with the Spirit of his mouth, and deſtroy with the brightneſs of his coming,</hi> all things below himſelf, which deſtruction every one ſhall ſee, and be convinced, it is the Lord. Saints and worldlings, your eyes ſhall be opened all ere long for to behold your ſelves firſt, &amp; then the Lord after; <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the eye which the Lord will give unto thee, ſhall as well behold all the glory of the fathers houſe, as it did cauſe thee to behold all thy evill, for this eye will carry thee into the ſecret chamber of God, there to behold all the inſide glory of thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and thou ſhalt not only ſee it, but be convinced all that is thine, and laid up for thee of old, yea, and thine for to wear upon thy ſhoulders in the day, when the Lord comes for to give reward unto his Saints, and them that fear his name, which day is haſting on amain, and it will not be long ere thou ſeeſt thy King, by the perfect light of God, called the light of an eye; And for thee oh world! thou ſhalt have an eye opened unto thee by the Lord, for to cauſe thee for to ſee him withall, and ſo to convince thee of all thy evill wayes, and of all thy evill deeds, and hard ſpeeches, which thou haſt moved withall towards his <hi>Iſrael;</hi> You may all read your doome in <hi>Jude,</hi> and hear there what the Lord ſaith; He ſaith that the next appearing after the cloudy, called the day of light, or the day of Chriſt, which day will be a day of conviction, a day of enlightning, throughout the world, of good and bad, a convincing day to all men of their wayes, <hi>Jude</hi> 15. <hi>ver.</hi> Therefore rejoyce oh <hi>Sion,</hi> and fear oh world, for the Lord is come near to Judgment, and it will be a ſpirituall one, attended with the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all light of God, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 4. 4. <hi>When the Lord ſhall have waſhed away the filth of the daughter of Sion, and ſhall have purged the blood of Jeruſalem by the Spirit of Judgment, and the ſpirit of burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:117206:13"/> This light of the Lord will be a reproving light, a light which ſhall cauſe men to ſee and be aſhamed, and ſee, and yet not be aſhamed, becauſe he will bring a further wrath upon them, it will be a reproving light, <hi>John</hi> 16. 8. <hi>When he comes he will reprove the world of ſin, of righteouſneſs, and of judgment.</hi> Oh the mighty, great, and unparallell fear that will fall upon all the world, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the light of God, which ſhall break forth upon them, for to behold the Lord withall: and as they ſhall behold him, ſo them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves too, and reade their own charge, and be their own Judges, <hi>Math.</hi> 12. 33. <hi>For by thy words thou ſhalt be juſtified, and by thy words thou ſhalt be condemned.</hi> That is, by thy own mouth, thou ſhalt be judged, either for ſalvation or damnation, and therefore Chriſt ſaith, <hi>The words that I have ſpoken, and you have rejected, ſhall judge you at the laſt day, John</hi> 12. 48. You are got into the laſt dayes, yea, unto the laſt dayes of the laſt dayes, that is, into the half time <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpake of, and that half time is almoſt out too, Oh world! and therefore a ſpirituall judgment is near to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to us all; And the words that Chriſt hath ſpoken, ſhall judge us all, that is, God will open the eye of the underſtanding of all, by his ſpirituall light, by the which light you ſhall know, and ſee, what you did reject, and what you have done in rejecting, and alſo what Chriſt ſaid, and how you all have anſwered him again, and alſo how you have lived, and you ſhall need no other Judge then the light of God, which ſhall ſhine upon your underſtanding and conſciences, for that ſhall give you light into all your wayes, in the which ye have walked, and this your enlightned underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and convinced conſciences ſhall condemne you all, that is, all fleſh; There is a myſterie, <hi>John</hi> 8. 9. <hi>And they that heard it being convinced in their conſciences, went out one by one;</hi> their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences bearing witneſs again, <hi>Romans</hi> 2. 15. <hi>Their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences alſo bearing witneſs, and their thoughts the meane while, either accuſing or excuſing,</hi> and a convinced conſcience either of good, or bad, lyeth in the underſtanding being enlightned, your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and conſciences oh Saints and worldlings! is all the book that God needs to uſe in the day of his ſpirituall judging of you, and behold he is coming to Judgment, and every eye ſhall ſee, by this light of God, every one ſhall be ſaved that have part in the firſt reſurrection, and by the ſame light every one ſhall be deſtroyed,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117206:14"/> that have not part in him: ſo that this light of God will bring ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and deſtruction, both at one time, unto the two hoaſts that ſtand at the right and left hand of God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33. 4, 5. The ſinners in <hi>Sion</hi> are afraid, fearfulneſs hath ſurpriſed the hypocrites, and who among us ſhall dwell with devouring fire? reade one of the next verſes, and it tels you who ſhall, and who ſhall not; the Lord is come, and coming ſtill for to deſtroy, and yet to ſave, and thats the reaſon why all fleſh doth ſo fear, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 39. 21. <hi>I will ſet my glory among the heathen, and all the heathen ſhall ſee my Judgments that I have executed, and my hand that I have laid upon them, Iſa.</hi> 66. 14. The hand of the Lord ſhall be known towards his ſervants, and his judgments towards his enemies, ye ſhall not only have judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but ſee the judgment of the Lord upon you, yea, eat your own fleſh, and drink your own blood, and the Lord will come for to open your eyes for to ſee it, <hi>And the glory of the Lord ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, and all fleſh ſhall ſee it together. Iſa.</hi> 40. 5. And again, that they may ſee, know, and underſtand together, that the hand of the Lord hath done this; you ſhall ſee the Lord oh ye nations! ere long in his Saints with great power, for to conſume thee oh world, and all that is in it, that will be the next diſpenſation of God after the cloudy; <hi>Sion</hi> ſtand up now and rejoyce, for thou haſt almoſt received double for all thy ſins, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 40. 2. Therefore comfort thy ſelf in thy God, for my King is very near bringing double joy, double peace, double reſt, and double glory, with a double ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all power, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 61. 7. And all ſhall be thine, and therefore gather to thee, And the reaſon is, becauſe the Lord will glorifie the houſe of his glory, and all ſhall call thee the City of the Lord, the <hi>Sion</hi> of the holy one of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> for the Lord will give thee ſuch a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall power, that by that power thou ſhalt conſume all the wicked in thee, ſo that no oppreſſor ſhall paſſe through thee any more, <hi>Zach.</hi> 9. 8. <hi>And I will encamp about my houſe, becauſe of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and becauſe of him that paſſeth by, and becauſe of him that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth, and no oppreſſor ſhall paſs through thee any more, for now have I ſeen with my eyes;</hi> this is a myſtery, the light of God is a conſuming, and a deſtroying light, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 11. 4. Hear oh world! your fall is begun, for your Prince that is your leader, is wounded by the light of God, and ſo wounded, that he bleeds all the way he goes, and ſo he will untill he hath bled himſelf to death, for the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117206:14"/> wound that is given him, is an uncurable wound, for it is given him by a mighty Prince, called the Lion of the Tribe of <hi>Judah, Sions King</hi> and your terrible Judge, and from this ariſes all your fear, and you know it not; Oh who ſhall ſtand before this great Judge, when he cometh out of Clouds into light, to judge with light and glory: why, this the Lord is coming near withall, and the day of the Lords light, will be the day of the Lords dividing, <hi>Joel.</hi> 3. 14. Or the day of the Lords great ſeparating, not only a dividing, or ſeparating the powers of evill men far from you oh Saints, or you from them, but a dividing or ſeparating two ancient warriers, fleſh and Spirit: ſo that you ſhall never learn war more; Why, oh ſoul! thou ſhalt never learn war more, for the Lord who is thy King, will conquer, all thy inſide enemies, as well as thy outſide enemies, and there ſhall be a great valley between ye both, and that is the reaſon why he comes with his glorious light, for to deſtroy all, and then for to make known all to you, <hi>Iſrael</hi> thou haſt been a long time under a vaile, the which vaile ſo covered thy fathers glory, that ye could not ſee, nor yet diſcern him, but now ye ſhall very ſuddenly, for it is neer taking away, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 25. 7. <hi>And he will deſtroy in this Mountain the face of the covering caſt over all people, and the vaile that is ſpread over all Nations;</hi> A ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall light brings a ſpirituall diſcerning along with it, <hi>Malachi</hi> 3. 18. <hi>Then ſhall ye return and diſcern,</hi> and <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 14. 16. <hi>And they that ſee ſhall narrowly look upon thee, and conſider thee, ſaying, Is this the man?</hi> Thy eyes ſhall be opened too oh world, and thou ſhalt ſee, and know, what <hi>Iſrael</hi> is, thou ſhalt know the Lords <hi>Sion,</hi> but with another manner of knowledge, then ever yet thou kneweſt them withall, and by that ſight thou ſhalt confeſs, this is the ſeed which God hath bleſſed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 69. 1. And as the light of the Lord in thee cauſes thee to know his <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo the light of the Lord in them ſhall deſtroy thee, as well as that in them, that bears not his image, and therefore is but ſtubble, and not fit for any thing but to to be deſtroyed by the light of God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10. 17. 18. <hi>And the light of Iſrael ſhall be for a fire, and his holy one for a flame, and it ſhall burne, and devoure his thornes and briars in one day;</hi> And as the Lord hath wounded the Prince of evill powers, ſo he hath wounded you all, and is revenging the blood of his Saints, Land the Lord is come for to make a full end of all things, but firſt with
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117206:15"/> Clouds, and by and by with light, for all ſhall be deſtroyed by the light of God; and I cannot but out of pure love give you warning of it: look therefore oh world about you, cannot ye ſee him yet? is <hi>Iſraels</hi> cloud between you and the Lord that ye cannot behold the Lord? why, the light of God will cauſe the clouds to remove, and then woe to be you, <hi>And they alſo which pierced him.</hi> Hear ye deſpiſers, and piercers of the Lords <hi>Sion,</hi> I will tell you what you have done, you have pierced the moſt precious Jewels the Lord hath, and pierced them ſo deep, that the wound is gone through the very ſide of God; And he is now coming, for to open thy eyes to cauſe thee to ſee the many wounds that thou haſt given him and them, and when that is repreſented, you ſhall ſee your ſelves wounded with a deadly and eternall wound, even unto death, and yet never for to die, in dying thou ſhalt dye, and yet not dy, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel.</hi> 9. 6. <hi>And in thoſe dayes men ſhall ſeek death, and ſhall not finde it,</hi> for the light of God will keep them alive for ever and ever, thy fall will be very great; Oh worldling! although you be as the Sunne of the morning, how art thou cutting down to the ground, which didſt once weaken the Nations? and thou art in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting out of the grave of ſecurity, where thou haſt lived and layen in peace, for many an Age. Therefore hear ye ſufferers for the Lord, he hath recorded thy ſufferings in his book, and them that pierced thee hath he in remembrance, and behold, he is coming to reward upon them the evill of their own wayes, and will plead with them here for thee, I, he will plead with all thy enemies temporall and ſpirituall, inſide and outſide ones, he remembers them all, and all ſhall fall and never riſe more, I, and that quickly, for the great day of the Lord is coming on amain; cannot yee ſee, hear, nor take notice, of the Lords goings, which proclaims to all the world that he is coming? ye are angry, and ye cannot tell with what, ye are diſpleaſed and ye cannot tell with whom, and the Lord is now coming to tell you, it is with himſelf that you are offended; There is a generation that muſt be offended, being out of the holy num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and therefore not honoured with that princely name <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo having no lot in the holy land, and therefore no entrance into the princely and heavenly Court, into which Chriſt is coming for to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all his up into, by the light of his father; Great will be thy joy oh ſoul, who art boloved of God, when this light of God
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117206:15"/> hath not only purified thee, but carried thee into the Court and manſion of heaven, and ſet thee down there with thy father, and thy King Jeſus, who is now come with Clouds, and by and by with light, watch ye therefore all ye ſons of <hi>Sion.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>And all kindreds of the Earth ſhall waile becauſe of him, even ſo Amen.</q>
            <p>Oh the unſpeakable walling and crying out there will be ere long! I even tremble to think how the earth will ring with the cries of enlightned ſoules, which have the light of God given them for no other end, then to be an eternall plague unto them, great crying, becauſe of great wrath, and this great wrath will cauſe great anger to ceaze upon your ſpirits, And your anger will ariſe from two cauſes, firſt from the Lords coming to judge thee by the light of himſelf in thee; Secondly, by the Lords coming for to give rewards unto his Saints, and to them that fear his name. Firſt from the Lords appearing for to judge you by the light of God in you; The day of the Lords appearing will be a day of great trouble, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it will be an eternall appearing, an appearing that ſhall bring along with it eternall light, eternall darkneſs with an eternall death too, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8. 22. <hi>And they ſhall look unto the Earth, and behold trouble and darkneſs, and dimneſs of an anguiſh, and they ſhall be driven into darkneſs;</hi> As eternall light, eternall darkneſs with eternall death makes up but an eternall plagues, ſo eternall light, eternall life, eternall joy, eternall peace, and an eternall glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, with an eternall knowing of God, as he is in himſelf, makes up an eternall ſalvation to the ſaved ones of God. Worldlings, where are you? what are you doing? are ye filling up the meaſures of your fathers wrath fuller yet? why, make haſt, for my King cannot come with a light, called the light of an eye, untill you have finiſhed the works of darkneſs, and if I be not miſtaken, you have almoſt, if not altogether finiſhed your work, for <hi>Sions</hi> King, and your terrible Judge makes haſt to come away, and me thinks I hear you begin to waile, but if not waile, you are filled with much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, fear and anger which is within one ſtep of wailing; the next ſight of my King will make you waile, then farewell all your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, rich treaſures, and worldly enjoyments, for all are condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117206:16"/> to dye already, and then they leave thee, and thou muſt leave them, I ſay, trouble, fear, and anger ye have in your hearts, and your hearts full of it, but ye cannot tell what is the cauſe of it, nor from whence it ariſeth; I will tell thee, Firſt, from the Lords coming to judge thee, and thy Judgment is begun, but it is a cloudy judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that is, an unſeen, and an unknown judgment, if it were made known to thee by the light of the Lord, what the Lord is adoing, and going ſtill about for to do to thee, and what haſt he makes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he hath done, thou wouldeſt not only fear, but waile, and let me tell thee one thing over again, all thy glory, wiſdom, riches, honor, and delight, with all thy other injoyments, are condemned by the Lord of the whole Earth, for to dy the death nay, they are dead, and that is the reaſon thou haſt ſo little comfort in the world, in this thy age; There is a great change made, inſtead of a ſweet ſmell there is a ſtinke, and inſtead of a girdle, a rent, inſtead of well-ſet haire, baldneſs, and inſtead of a ſtomacher, a girding with ſackcloth, and burning inſtead of beauty, ſo that all is out of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, by reaſon of the cloudy day of God, and when once the Lord appeareth with light, then will thy wailing begin, but never end, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the light that God will give thee, will be a light that will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver goe out, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. 11. <hi>And the ſmoak of their torment aſcendeth up for ever and ever, and they have no reſt day nor night;</hi> thy City and thy glory oh world is falling, is falling, is falling <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. 8. And now thy great ſtrength is gone, and therefore nothing but trouble com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the roome, by reaſon of the Lords appearing; And it will not be long ere the earth ſhine, or be enlightned with the Lords glory, and the ſhining and enlightning is for to let thee know, that thy kingdome and glory is going, being but a Babylonian glory, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 1. 2. <hi>And I ſaw an Angel come down from Heaven, having great power, and the earth was enlightned with his glory, and he cryed with a ſtrong voyce ſaying,</hi> Babylon <hi>the great is fallen, is fallen, and become the habitation of Devils;</hi> Thou oh world! haſt the myſterie of iniquity dwelling in thee, and by thy myſterious iniquities, haſt carried the Lords <hi>Iſrael</hi> captive at thy will, for many thouſand years, and now the years of thy power is up, and the day of thy ruling is at an end, becauſe all thy actions have been unrighteous actions, and all thy wayes and paths, which thou haſt walked in, have been ſinfull wayes and paths, and therefore now after thy
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117206:16"/> iniquity, woe be unto thee, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. 23. <hi>Woe be unto thee indeed ſaith the Lord,</hi> for thy ſins have reached up to heaven, and have raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Lord of hoſts out of his place, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33. 10. <hi>Now will I ariſe ſaith the Lord, now will I be exalted, now will I lift up my ſelf,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold now he is come down, and is with thee, to be exalted over thee, and to recompenſe upon thee according to thy works, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 5. <hi>For her ſins have reached up to Heaven, and God hath remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred her iniquity,</hi> your wayes oh ye ſons of men, and all ye rulers of the Earth have been, and are ſtill <hi>Canaanitiſh</hi> wayes, and ye have all run greedily after the error of <hi>Balaam</hi> for reward, but in the end will periſh in the gainſaying of <hi>Core, Jude</hi> 11. <hi>ver.</hi> Thy end is now begun, I, the end of your evill wayes oh Saints, and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, is come up before the Lord, and what do you think to doe? for <hi>Job,</hi> whom the Lord honored with the name of my ſervant, and faithfull one, and juſt in all his wayes, yet though ſo, when the Lord who is a God of ſo pure eyes that cannot behold iniquity, did but once riſe up, <hi>Job</hi> feared, with a ſaying, <hi>What then ſhall I do? Job</hi> 31. 14. <hi>When God ariſeth up and when he viſiteth, what ſhall I anſwer him?</hi> If the <hi>Sion</hi> of God do as it were fear, what wilt thou do oh world? then the Lord ariſes up to the prey, and to gather thee for eternall ruine, and to judge thee with an eternall Judgment, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with a juſt ſentence, and a juſt reward like thy works; Oh all ye workers of iniquity; and by the light of God ye ſhall ſee it, and then your wailing will begin. What aileſt thou oh world for to waile, why, do ye not know oh ye bleſſed of the Lord the light of him who is your King; and therefore raigneth over you, and in you, even he whom I ſcorned and rejected with a ſaying, <hi>This man ſhall not rule over me,</hi> hath wounded me to the heart by this light; and this light by which he hath enlightned me, carrieth me forward and backward, backward and forward, juſt as he did <hi>David</hi> after he had committed adultery with <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> and ſlew <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi> with the Sword, he carrieth me backward, to behold all my evill deeds which I have done; and the many wounds that I have given him and you, And alſo carrieth me forward to behold what once was offered me, what mercies and what bleſſings, what glory, and what life, what peace and what reſt, with an eternall ſalvation with your eternall King, but now rejected of him, by my own rebellious and ſcornfull denying of him and you, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117206:17"/> all this by the light of God, and this light of God cauſes me to waile, with an everlaſting wailing, and therefore what conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on can be like unto mine? why, no condition can be like unto thine, for thou art doubly miſerable, and therefore ſhalt be doubly plagued by that light that ſhall come down from the Lord to ſhine upon thee.</p>
            <p>Secondly, from the Lords coming for to give rewards to his Saints, what a plague will it be to thee oh world for to behold Gods <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whom thou thoughtſt not worthy to live, nor yet the remembrance of them in the earth for to be, that they ſo little eſteemed of the earth among men, ſhould come to be cloathed with ſuch glory, and righteous robes, and to be inveſted with all the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of heaven, called the glory of the father? didſt thou never hear of <hi>Mordecai,</hi> and the royall cloathing he wore, and the horſe that he rid upon, and the Crown Royall which was ſet upon his head, and the Proclamation which was made before him, by one of the moſt royalleſt Princes of that Court, and of the ring that was put upon his finger? this is a myſterious type, theſe are the Lords <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicai's,</hi> that I now tell thee of, and they ſhall all of them ride up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wings of the Lords free grace, ere long, although thou now diſeſteemeſt of them, and they ſhall have given them all manner of change of raiment, called the white robes, though for the preſent their cloathing is but ragged and filthy and an old cloathing, thou art angry with them now, and envieſt them with thy very heart, although they do but bear a dark Image of God, and their light is but an imperfect light that they have yet O world! And though their gifts, knowledg, and underſtanding be imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and their cloaths ragged, yet thou hateſt that in them they have. Well, thou ſhalt not hate this imperfect image long, for the Lord is coming for to take them away; and methinks I hear a voyce crying in my ears, Take away, take away, take away, theſe filthy rags, <hi>Zach.</hi> 3. 3, 4. And he ſpake to them that ſtood by him, Take away thoſe filthy Garments which they ſtand before the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel withal, they ſhall be ſuddenly taken away; for that is the reaſon why <hi>Michael</hi> the Prince ſtands up, that Arch-Angel; and that is the reaſon why the breaker up is come up, it is I ſay, For to take away all our putrified and corrupt cloathing; and upon the remove, there will be trouble in thee, O <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And now they are riſen, it will
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117206:17"/> not be long ere it is finiſhed, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 24. It is but as it were a ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty weeks; before it ſhall be done, ſeventy weeks are determined upon thy people, and upon thy holy City; to finiſh tranſgreſſions, and to make an end of ſin, and to bring in everlaſting righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. This is a Myſtery; you have this Myſtery opened in part in <hi>Heb.</hi> 9 28. unto them that look for him; he ſhall appear the ſecond time without ſin unto ſalvation. It will not be long, ere this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be fulfilled upon thee, O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for thou art the City ſpoken of in <hi>Daniel.</hi> The world is old<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the Cities of the Nations are old too, and therefore every thing is ſtepping his laſt ſtep, and looking his laſt look, and a joying his laſt joy, and in ſpeaking his laſt words, and in breathing out his laſt breath. O World, thou art dying, thou art dying, and all within thee too; for the end of all things is at hand, I, and the beginning of all things is at hand; the beginning of a new look, a new joy, and ſo a new enjoyment; a new ſong, called the ſong of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> a new language, even the holy Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of Heaven, a new righteouſneſs, a new peace, a new ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a new glory, a new breath, a new life, even the holy Life of God; therefore what will thou do? O World, I cannot but weep for thee; for the Bride, and the Bridegroom, will meet ere long, and then there will be no room for thee among them. The Bride by the power and light of the <hi>Lord,</hi> is a making her ſelf ready, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it if thou canſt; for it is a Scripture phraſe, and the Bride ſhall be made, as fit a bride for the bridegroom, as the bridegroom is for the bride; and then meet they ſhall, and ſhall be both as glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and comely, as all the glory in Heaven and Earth can make them; and they ſhall wear this, the inſide, perfect glory of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in thy ſight, and this ſhall be one of thy plagues, I ſay; that the children of the light will have a glorious white robe given them, and they ſhall wear this their robe in thy ſight, being the children of the day, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 5. And for thee, O World, thou art not ſo in the dark, but that the Lord can, and will enlighten thee to behold <hi>Sions</hi> glory; and therefore, he ſaith, Every eye ſhall ſee him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I, thou ſhalt ſee him, and them; Why? who ſhall we ſee, you bleſſed of God? why? you ſhall behold the bride, and the bridegroom; that is, Chriſt and his Saints, the King and his Subjects, the Father, and the Children, the Head, and the Members, the King, and the Kings, the lover and the beloved, both cloathed with one glory,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117206:18"/> from the Father of glory; and then the deſire of the Lord my King, will be fulfilled. <hi>Father, make them one, as thou and I am one, John</hi> 17. 21, 22, 23, 24. Pray reade there, O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and that will tell thee what condition thou wilt be in ere long; for the height, and breadth, depth, and length of the love of Chriſt, ſhall be known to you, and ye ſhall be filled with the fulneſs of God: How doſt thou like this, O World? I muſt tell thee one thing more, and when that one thing comes to be fulfilled; it will be as an Arrow in thy heart, and ſo a hearty plague upon thee; for thou ſhalt know, and ſee all this by the light of God, but ſhalt receive no more of it to thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, then that <hi>Lord</hi> did, which ſtood in the gate of <hi>Samaria,</hi> after that long deſtructive ſiege was raiſed; and that bread was to be had, who was trodden down in the gate, and died; he ſaw indeed, but never taſted of it, read 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 7. 2, 19, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0. Thou ſhalt ſee it with thy eyes, but ſhalt not eat thereof: So, O World, thou mayeſt ſtand without the gate, or at the gate, and look in and ſee the glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ones of God, but never enter in for to joy with them; for thou art the dog, and without are dogs, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 15. within is perfect joy, without perfect wailing; and the Word telleth you, That the Reaſon of the Worlds wailing will be, by reaſon of the appearing of Jeſus Chriſt in his brightneſs. The cloudy appearing of Jeſus Chriſt is a dark appearing, and a dark appearing is an unſeen, and an unknown appearing to all men as men; and what the eye ſeeth not, the heart grieveth not for, that's a common phraſe among you; but you ſhall have eyes given you for to ſee the Lord withal; and then the ſight of him, will cauſe wailing in you. The Lords wrath is begun with clouds, but ſhall end with light, the Spiritual light of God, and then thy plagues will be perfected. The Lord hath waited upon you long, O Kings, Princes, Rulers, Magiſtrates; and all ye powers of the earth after what name or title ſoever mentioned; with all ye Miniſters and people, I ſay, my King hath waited upon you very long, and ſuffered you to fill up your wickedneſs, and to make mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure up to the brim; and when thou haſt done, <hi>Sions</hi> King will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with a ſaying. Put in the ſickle, for the harveſt is ripe; get ye down, for the fat is overflown; their wickedneſs is great, and come to perfection; and wickedneſs perfected, will be recompenced with plagues perfected: The Lord hath begun to pour out his vials of plagues upon thee, O World; and he will never leave pouring out,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117206:18"/> until he hath perfected them all; for there is a perfection of plagues, as well as a perfection of beauty; there is a full knowing all miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, as well as a full knowing all myſteries; and the time is haſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on apace by the <hi>Lord,</hi> in the which, both ſhall be known: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all ye powers of the earth, make haſt and do that ye do quickly; for when you have poured forth all that you have to pour, and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled all that you have to fulfil, upon Chriſt and his Members, that you have no more to fulfil; then the <hi>Lord</hi> will begin to pour out all that he hath to pour, and to fulfil all that he hath to fulfil upon you, that is, All the plagues written in this Book, <hi>Revel.</hi> 22. 18. And when the <hi>Lord</hi> hath done all that he hath to do, and fulfilled or poured forth upon you all that he hath to pour, then ye ſhall be left in your miſery for ever: and then the word, <hi>Even ſo Amen,</hi> ſhall be finiſhed upon you.</p>
            <p>The word, <hi>Even ſo Amen,</hi> hath a joyful ſound, and a terrible ſound. Hear, O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ye Nations of the Earth; hear ye Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and all ye powers of the World; Ye are fit for nothing, but to be deſtroyed by the light of God; your very actions ſpeak out, your deſtruction is neer at hand; for death is written upon all your footſteps, and the word, <hi>Even ſo Amen,</hi> will prove your dreadful doom: For when the <hi>Lord</hi> hath poured upon you all plagues, and hath ſeparated all his ſheep far from you, and you from them, and withdrawn himſelf, after that he hath enlightened you with an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal light, for to be your eternal plague; and to perfect your plagues, you ſhall have darkneſs, and light mixed together, eternal light, and eternal darkneſs; and darkneſs ſhall cover thee for ever, even thick darkneſs, that <hi>Jude</hi> ſpake of, To whom is reſerved the blackneſs of darkneſs for ever; and when all this is done the <hi>Even ſo Amen</hi> is finiſhed.</p>
            <p>And now hear one word more oh <hi>Iſrael,</hi> behold the Lord my King is coming, and yet come too; And at his preſence the world ſhakes, and mountains tremble, and the end of his coming is for to finiſh upon thee, all that he hath for to finiſh, and to give thee of the fatneſs of his houſe, to cloath thee with the perfect heavenly glory, and to give thee that, that ſhall never be taken from thee, nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ſhaken, but remain with thee for ever, thy heavenly King is coming, and in his hand there is for thee ſpirituall and heavenly bleſſings, I, and he is coming with both hands full, and they hold all
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:117206:19"/> the inſide treaſure in heaven and earth, and when all that that is for thee, whether it be wiſdom or knowledg, glory or bleſſings, is given unto thee, and cloathed up thee, according to the full and perfect gift of God, then the word, <hi>Even ſo Amen,</hi> will be finiſhed. The word, <hi>Even ſo Amen,</hi> ends all, it puts an end to all thy ſufferings and ſorrows, and it puts an end to all thy faith, and heavenly hope; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thy heavenly King hath brought unto thee, the unſeen ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and thou haſt received that, that thou ſo long hopedſt for; and if we hope for that we ſee not, then we do with patience wait for it: And Faith it is the ſubſtance of things hoped for, and the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of things not ſeen; but thou ſhalt have a thouſand times more then ever thou couldſt believe or hope for; and when that not ſeen, and not believed, and not hoped for ſubſtance and treaſure, which the <hi>Lord</hi> hath laid up for thee, is given to thee, then the word <hi>(Even ſo Amen)</hi> will be finiſhed upon thee. I ſhall therefore cloſe up all with a ſaying, <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, neither hath it entered into the heart of man, to conceive the things that God hath prepared for them that love him.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
